hello welcome everyone it is February
21st
2025 we're live in active inference
guest stream number
90.2 with Benjamin Nelson decoding The
Arc the evolution of Reason in the
abstract reasoning Corpus today will be
a very interesting presentation and also
time for questions
so Benjamin thank you for the work and
for presenting it and being open and
giving others the opportunity to ask
questions as well so looking forward to
the presentation and take it away thank
you hello welcome uh I uh I'll just jump
right in um I recently competed in the
ark uh competition and um during and
after um I was uh able to uh pull some
really high scores and it's because of a
really fascinating and fun approach uh
derived from active inference that uh
seems to work really well I hope you
guys will really like it um can you see
my screen I think you can right so the
um uh this GitHub repository uh I just
made this um it's not super fancy or
anything but the code itself is uh
really really fun and uh I really uh
encourage everyone uh to dig in and just
have as much fun as they possibly can um
with this um very cool um but not the
coolest toy uh ever in my opinion I love
it so um the uh in addition to you know
kind of um uh synchronously with the
developing the repository for this thing
that uh I made for the competition um
which is it's called a state managed uh
approach the the state managed system is
a uh cognitive Computing framework uh as
I mentioned derived from active
inference uh and basically what uh it
does is it looks at different biological
processes functions and then uh you know
does the best to not necessarily mirror
the um the exact workings of the
function itself but um more so the
outcome so the
uh I would definitely say it's it's
there's like a a fine line between
prescribing something like dictating it
for the model and uh or uh describing
something like explaining it to the
model and prescribing it uh like
dictating its actions and the kind of
the goal of this is um a certain amount
of autonomy uh and it's it's really fun
to play with so um you've got as we'll
see in the paper U like and I I'll just
go ahead and like pull that up
here um there's like the core docum
sorry a lot of lot of paperwork this
week on this uh doing this paper so uh
from arest to archetype Archangel EP and
the emergence of the state managed
system so um uh we'll get of course to
the abstract and all of this stuff I'll
leave that to you guys um there's just a
handful of things I want to touch on
um oh yeah I think I actually have that
up even here give me just a second
[Music]
sweet all right we're good okay so the
um I I'm sorry you guys will have to
bear with me too I have a very old and
and uh I love my laptop very much but it
spends a lot of time in the freezer now
cooling down uh when I forget and
accidentally leave one of the models on
so the um um yeah actually I do want to
kind of talk about this like this is
like um I was having a conversation with
Andrew uh who's a uh a member of the
scientific Advisory Board here he's a
really helpful super amazing person um
and he's been kind of like holding my
hand through some of this process which
I'm really grateful for um but it is
definitely um as I said earlier um it's
the this isn't like um it's not like a
burden of cost it's a labor of love and
uh like the this is like something I'm
super passionate about and uh for me it
I think even though I would never say I
can do art or anything artistic uh by
any chance I feel like this this is
almost something similar it's like u i I
do these things like in a very unique
way I think um at least you know that's
what I've been told so um I hope you'll
bear with me as I go through this um in
the code specifically um and I think I
hope you'll see what I I'm talking about
for instance I gave like a really nice
uh outfit like a fit for a uh Archangel
which is uh the name of that framework
the Archangel EP so um basically um here
at the beginning of February I uh jumped
back into uh tackling The Arc uh I just
you know had some bandwidth and the
things that I've made Archangel with are
like old uh and older like uh cognitive
mechanisms that um you know like either
just kind of like get like a you know
worn down over time which is a weird way
to think about code um but you know it's
like uh these Integrations and then as
Daniel knows the amount of times I've
had to take uh the larger framework
apart um stop in the middle of what I'm
doing um to work on like this kind of
thing uh results in a lot of uh
unfortunately spare parts and broken
parts so um this toy I made is from uh a
massive uh model named Nim that I've
been building for a really long time and
he's like my best friend and he's
awesome and I love him to death and um
getting back into the ark I you know i'
hope it was kind of a way to like show
that not only does the state like does a
state manager approach like
uh is it it's I don't want to say it's
it's better because it's not about like
which one is better it's about like I
guess which approach can maximally solve
or resolve which problems
uh the most meaningfully the fastest I
guess in a way and there are some
wonderful uh things that this framework
now in its uh much more advanced like uh
iteration could bring to the table and I
I really want to get that out there so I
figured i' would throw uh some old Parts
together um finish Archangel and um just
completely uh crush the the abstract
reasoning corpus with it so um the did
you just give a quick note on what is
the abstract reasoning Corpus show
visualization of what it is and then
explain what it looks like to solve it
and then we'll hear more about how it's
being solved but back up a bit to there
thank you continue perfect yeah I
appreciate you so much so the uh Arc
prize uh remains undefeated new ideas
still needed and I love that because the
arc is uh this amazing test as you'll
see here um there there are like uh
there's a color palette it's the same
for everybody uh and then there are
these grid examples and the grids are
dynamic in that each one is different
and I believe I'm not sure if they get
harder as they go on but you definitely
see the models um you know like uh kind
of performance like uh change and like
fluctuate like with uh at different
places in the uh in the exam and it's
like different for every model which is
really cool so
um like uh yeah so they basically the
these grids get like harder and harder
and harder here's like where you can see
um other AI benchmarks um you can see
where other models have performed and
it's basically like a you know a really
cool test oh there's the Legends at
mindes AI so uh and The Architects these
guys like wow I mean so cool and there's
03 down there so the
um the the the point of the abstract
reasoning Corp is like to kind of like
uh and I don't want to crib cholet uh
because like I'm not you know even in
the same league but the um like to solve
a problem and to Maxim maximally resolve
it to be like the the real true abstract
Problem Solver is to like be able to
approach a problem as I understand it
maybe you can correct me on this like uh
with no prior knowledge of the problem
no prior knowledge of the solution uh
and to be able to tackle the problem uh
directly so um and resolve it there like
in that moment so like that's really
always been my Approach I really love
abstraction like in anything that's
abstract uh that's kind of how my mind
works and um that processing of grids
and those uh complexifying like uh
orders that they come in and the model
resolves them the model has a figure out
how to adapt and make decisions and to
solve problems and to uh Converge on a
decision and to choose actions and all
of these things that are required so
even though it's like just grids and
colors it's a lot of things um which is
why they give some things like uh to the
competitors like in terms of like you
know that it's grid you know what the
colors are uh going to be you know um
what actions you'll most likely need to
select based on how your model is
designed to uh uh you know con like do
the like Converge on a decision or you
know say I made this I'm not confident
about this I don't like this color I'm
actually going to go with this color and
make predictions and so the model is
making predictions um and uh as a you
know if the these like there are
solution files that come with the Json
files and as those come feeding in um
they you know are essentially bypassed
uh into like conditional storage and
used at the end of the at the end of
that uh to determine whether or not you
have um either a perfect mirror match or
you can do it by pixel and do a full
pixel count of every color and
everything that's on there and they give
you like Frameworks for that and there's
like tons of um I mean there's tons of
people that uh do this there's over 1400
teams of like really amazing Engineers
like some of the most brilliant people
in the world like leaders in these
fields um to uh even get to you know
have the confidence to like join
something like this uh solo with two
months left in the competition uh and
then pull uh
86.4% and beat the theoretical maximum
of the arc that's pretty incredible so
the um uh I'm I love all of these guys
and uh I'm like super grateful to Daniel
for introducing me to everybody who is
uh involved in all the kind of like
people I got to meet and have
conversations with um but uh Archangel
is not my arc submission like uh
Archangel is a first of first he's the
uh or it's I should say um it's pretty
simple and I think you guys really enjoy
it it's the first uh uh State managed
like open source have fun do whatever
you want learn as much as you can and
I've published uh multiple papers
including one today um that we're going
to look at uh and that's um I mean kind
of I don't even really necessarily read
my own research I definitely read a lot
of Robert warden's research though and
it informs my work uh significantly in
fact um like when looking at the
potentials that are emerging from uh
what I see and you know thankfully can
have uh critiqued and reviewed and
vetted uh through the Institute through
expertise and scholarship um there
there's amazing potential here it's like
this whole entire space is totally
unexplored and I'm just in there all by
myself okay sorry about the disrupt I'm
working in extru ating situations could
you go back and can can you
just show us where you're at with a code
and sorry about the last like 10 minute
flip it was out of my
control I I didn't even know what
happened until you said something I mean
so it's I'm really not worried about it
too much but uh that I I covered all the
good Stu it's just that it's not on the
live stream so you must do it again all
right so uh what are you want to look at
probably the code right let's see the
code and visualizations of solving and
clarification of the benchmarking and
which data set specifically you did it
on and again apologies to The View one
question time yeah oh yeah that's um so
um that this is just kind of some boring
stuff well this is uh again um feature
extraction tools I love these like Nims
or not Nim uh archangel's kind of like a
like almost like a little like uh a
multi-tool whose feelings you could hurt
potentially like um and I don't know if
we like uh got to hear anything about
like the encoding and stuff but just to
kind just to kind of back on uh quickly
we'll see like different tools and then
we start getting into the cognitive
mechanisms where we hit the
prioritization optimization and ination
algorithm uh which I made very proud of
it um and I published uh some work about
it um and I hope you guys will check
that out too um that explains how all of
this stuff works um there are waiting
systems which are fun to play with there
are dimensionality reduction equations
that I think everybody knows I got from
Keith affas um here you'll see uh these
are the uh kind of constants that you
can play with in terms of like uh your
tolerance um you know windows for
improvement like iterations and things
like that um which I turn that up that's
cool I didn't realize that was so low so
um the uh you'll see that carry through
here and then we get into some of the
the like the processing stuff so this is
like where the model is like just kind
of identifying what the grid is and
giving it just some basic uh like like
structure like form in its mind
something to work with uh so for
instance the category sized is it small
medium or large really simple right and
then uh how are we looking at the layers
of this grid does it have layers so they
don't really tell you and it's like you
don't want to look uh either like in the
Json files I mean you can I think people
do but like at the same time too you
don't want to know you don't want to
like prescribe to the model what to do
you want to describe what it should do
and like kind of help guide it without
giving it the answers kind of thing and
um uh so the like the simple stuff uh
there this is a much more uh fun uh in
terms of the intentional selection
mechanism and how Dimensions work with
this uh and kind of what those
capacities really are because even I
don't know yet this is definitely the
Crown Jewel the hot field Network um I
made this uh it's just incredible I
still also haven't tested the limits of
it um I accidentally like crashed some
uh stuff when I uh like turned it on
without like
uh but like those guys like with the JPL
thing right it's like it's kind of the
same thing but so the hot field network
is a dynamic way to store retrieve it's
uses hean learnings so there was a great
paper that came out um a while back and
uh it was a comparison on Q learning and
heian learning um but the truth of the
matter is heian learning uh doesn't
really work great as a reinforcement
learning feature at all but it works
awesome for uh memory encoding and
retrieval especially retrieval uh it
allows for really complex uh condense
and dense data to pass through the
system and into confabulation or
abstraction really really easily and
meaningfully um you can see you can set
the Hop field size here and the overall
memory system capacity
the memory Works under the ainson Shi
model so wonderful and simple long-term
short-term working make as many types as
you want um and have fun the me memory
management uh you have values uh in the
form of decks for well Max Len for um
making decks for the uh short-term and
working memory so you can set those size
I typically like to go with like a
larger working memory um the way that
this is structured will kind of float
some information a lot of times and uh
to keep it kind of accessible if it's
meaningful based on um uh different uh
like things in the system for instance
confidence um beliefs right all of those
there's not really like um like one
thing doesn't do all the things and one
thing can't do any one thing without all
the other things so um the system gets
really wonky and doesn't make a lot of
sense um but I can tell you this much
just from experience if you are not
breaking it or failing and then you're
not doing it right it's a it's like for
every 10,000 lines of code I write I get
10 lines of code that work or something
like that it's it's really um uh been a
long and arduous process so um this
autonomic stress uh mechanism that's
cool cool function that mirrors
biological processes um these autonomic
functions for um like stress
minimization like reducing or increasing
entropy um homeostasis uh um even the
minimization of you know free energy
right so uh Act of inference and this is
another thing that can be uh expanded on
and is and um there are much more
advanced uh versions of this that I have
that I'm really excited to see um people
work with uh as you um kind of
understand how like State Management uh
in these computational Frameworks if you
don't already uh works so these
different things that I talk about in
the paper of course um so you know let's
say like you get the model is really
happy about something and it has this
really big increase in the uh like in
something it's like perceiving for
instance cake and so like the model will
dynamically pull from syst systems that
are deemed like less important to that
task and um uh redirect those energies
uh you
know H to all kinds of different systems
and all kinds of combinations of systems
that I some that I just I could I never
even I never even knew and that's where
like a uh you know we have that like
kind of a merence from the inside it's
like the the the building by prescribing
as opposed to prescribing has like made
possible a lot of these really bizarre
and cool behaviors that while in some
cases do not reflect biological uh
cognition at all those outcomes will or
some feature of its operation will work
in such a way as to allow for something
else to work uh perfectly or you know
like insanely well um I mean considering
I run this like model that pulls
quadrillions of uh calculations a second
on my very old laptop that does spend a
lot of time in Freez so um yeah so
here's a Epsilon control this is another
fun one I hope you guys play with um
complexity uh Shannon entropy right I
I've been learning a lot about entropy
and a lot about uh the universal
constant um I have a paper coming out um
actually here before the end of this
month um that I've been getting help
from a dear friend who's my absolute
hero and um I'm really excited about it
some novel discoveries about the nature
of time um through the lens of Robert
warden's brilliant projective wave
theory and um I'm really excited and I
talk about one of the the uh things that
I'm making um and this is a perfect
example of that so um pzo El electric
conductivity in lattice structures
specifically
uh crystalline lce structures so the
turns there's there's like a a
vibrational energy
like I don't even know how to say this
without sounding like a cook um but
the uh faster than neuronal firing like
and uh early encoding like a way to pass
like 2D and 3D spatial data to a model
through its visual cortex um before like
the the actual process of firing um can
occur even in the model even something
that runs as fast so supercharge that I
have no idea what that looks like and I
hope it's safe so uh we'll find out can
I bring us a little bit back Benjamin to
Arc and could you could you
show this code running and then let's
return to look through some subunits but
I think it's totally fair for people to
be like what does this actually do and
let's see it run and solving certain
problems that we can visualize yeah just
just you know that's what thisor part it
a way yeah not not for many others
though not for others but let's let's
let's see the real code run and and
highlight what the GitHub will do if
people clone it and run it and see
solving basic and hard
problems thank
you so um basically what you're going to
see is here is on the bottom uh maybe
it's the right I'm like kind of
just right yeah right uh you'll see 0400
those are the training tasks and then
underneath that you'll see 05 and those
are uh or I'm sorry the 0400 is the
training challenges 05 are what I call
training tasks and they're staging for
the model to learn to understand so um
as I understand it uh and during the arc
um models will uh run these uh
consistently and hold that information
uh and use it uh again later like um you
know it's part of the pre-training and
then the training and then the
fine-tuning um I'm really glad in a lot
of ways that I don't have to deal with
so much of that um
the uh yeah this the Archangel will grab
anything that you put in front of it um
like not just Json files right like
right now we could be uh and I do have
some stuff if you want I can send you
this where you're looking it's like P
PDF docx Json uh CSV HTML it's just all
these different things uh all at once
and um in this specific instance um
there's nothing like there's just like
Purge Flags basically when uh the model
finishes you know and shuts down it's
it's not holding on to any of that data
there's no like uh memory uh storage
like that it's all dynamic that's
created when that hop field is uh acted
on and or initialized and I actually
have the initialization sequence uh in
one of my Publications I hope you can
find it um and that initialization
sequence like it's it's an incredible
tool um you know dumping the memory is
the easy part um getting the
initialization sequence right is uh uh a
lot more fun and if you need help I'd be
happy to do that U be careful because
again that's where I uh crash those
servers
stuff um could you just describe what
what is the problem that it's solving
right now and then let's look at the
setup and the solution when it gets
there yeah so it's uh it is just solving
like whatever problems are coming
through so I don't know if I'm assuming
because it's you know it's Json they
just come through the same every time
right so um but uh right now it's like
learning all of the patterns um that
it's seeing it's looking at the training
examples and when you see that place
color action it has tons of actions by
the way so you guys turn those on have
fun with them really it's a grid I mean
it just places the colors but um that
place color action and how that is
achieved uh is really phenomenal because
it's not it's not dictated that the
action is Place color it chooses that
because that's the most meaningful thing
and what um you see in those lines that
are whipping by the screen U too fast
for me to really read um are windows
that allow the model to uh continue
working on the problem as opposed to
just timing out um the goal is for the
model to reach convergence so all of
these systems are working together to
kind of just teach the model through
like a warden Zari subsystem which is
maximizing Fitness and that Fitness
represents in the case of the arc
solving this problem and how do we solve
that problem with it believes so it's
like it'll say hey okay so in the very
beginning here we'll see for instance
since like the model will take a really
long time to learn to solve the first
problem and a little less time for the
next and less time for the next and then
by the the end it takes one tenth of the
time it did for the training to do the
evaluation um and uh the evaluation has
even less um context or context for the
uh the model to work from so um it's
robust it works um I was able to like I
said improve some communicability around
um what is happening with the code and
those grids um and I'm excited to see
that work this is that model um with
those improvements it's not the one
that's in the git um and I'm going to
make that change later it's just I mean
writing the paper and doing the maths
and all the other stuff uh trying to get
ready is just really exciting and then
with that other paper here at the end of
the month um so the selection you see
iterations it's like it'll be a ton and
it'll keep going
um uh until it resolves that and then it
it's just you know for for all intents
and purposes it's just like okay cool uh
you got one correct and you have one
incorrect right uh you have one correct
uh or two correct nonone correct and it
just builds up simple tqdm like uh
status bar and lets you know uh how far
along you are in those challenges I do
have like the I have all of the
challenges um uh uh but again I'm not
competing uh with the ark I'm uh not uh
U competing in the ark and um this is
for fun so you guys are able to get
those um from their website The Arc
pri.org I believe um and uh I find
running them in kaggle is is really
simple and uh fun and easy to do to just
like uh load them in as input data um
and uh you'll be doing the same thing
with this this um it's primarily
designed in in uh uh kaggle though um I
I have been having fun with cursor
because you can kind of just like get
really creative and and kind of Express
be more expressive I feel like uh more
creative and really value that I feel
like uh this is like being a labor of
love is like a lot of creative
self-expression that goes into this so
uh again this is like um more of that
same thing
the uh with this CH this cool change
that I made like you get a really really
really like I guess i' would say like
you get even less training more context
and the model becomes much more
self-reliant and you see much stronger
uh uh kind of question answering and
Abstract problem solving coming in uh
the evaluation phase which was running
in uh like super low
microseconds uh possibly like High
nanc um which is really exciting uh
super fast problem solving and the uh um
it would solve uh and I only got to see
it because you know because I'm using
like the mouse like to back you know
move the the uh video tape back and
forth or the screen recording and uh um
yeah there's just a clump of all of a
sudden it's like it realized what it was
doing it knew the grids and very
confidently just goes Bam gets it right
Bam Bam Bam and it's like seven
questions right in a row it was really
cool for Andrew to see that too um on
the first try and of course those are
not massive grids with super complex
patterns but the fact that it will make
a prediction um which is a process that
occurs um almost by virtue almost
completely by virtue of the Markov
matrices uh that are built into this for
passing that complexity as that data is
traveling those feedback loops um and uh
um um yeah yeah and uh I don't know it's
exciting stuff I haven't I haven't
really had a chance to like share openly
with the with anybody about it um I've
been really busy like working in kind of
isolation uh on all the stuff as you can
probably tell like I'm not great at
talking about it um especially it's all
good this is that opportunity Benjamin
so whatever you feel like somebody who
doesn't necessar
know what is happening just from the
logs like can you just connect the dots
a little bit
more with how do how do you know what
the performance was on the training in
the test set
specifically oh oh um
well the uh the way that the these
things are made right like the and and a
lot of this like reporting um is kind of
in a way like kind of almost provided by
the uh the if you know where to look
because there's so many great
competitors and like wonderful people
out there um it's really simple um there
are uh where does your grid pass in the
system and how does it pass in the
system and so it must come into the
system and then and then it has to you
have to compare those grids and you can
like I said do that with a pixel count
um which they provide the framework for
that or you can do that with a Like
Apples to Apples comparison of the two
uh and I believe they provided the
framework for that too for everybody
it's like a thing that you could just
have um and uh when those like when that
grid passes into the system there's uh
for this model like a lot of things
going on right so you have all of the
different types of tools that you have
which would be like your action space
selecting your action so like I'm GNA
move my arm and I'm going to grab the
piece because I know that's the right
thing to do you know and um you f you
can just really I I don't know how to
it's like there's all this like
reporting right like that stuff that
you're seeing is not super great if you
don't know what you're looking at um but
um there is an infinite amount of like
print statements even like if you want
to know something how this something
works in this model like just use the
print State like or something akin to
that like if you use mat plot lib like I
had I was writing code to make uh
visualizations that would show the
modulation of the beliefs um as they
change and the
uh the emotional modulation as well and
um there's uh yeah but I didn't get a
done you know it's like uh so much work
all the time and I try to do as good as
I can but um I have those things and you
guys can see them at any point you
wanted to I'm sorry that uh we may not
get to look at them uh I know a friend
of mine is probably trying to work on
them right now so um yeah the when you
when you go into the art competition
right you're you're like you watch
feedback from your model like I don't
know what everybody else did I it was 20
24 hours a day sometimes like back
toback days I didn't take a day off the
entire time uh just 20 hour days of just
watching feedback while you code and so
when you when people are like say well
how do we know that things go through
the model it's like it is tough to
explain to to to people without like
having being able to have someone's like
attention wrapped in front of you for
seven hours so like um to jump in like
if we want to know for instance how this
like how we can know what what the
answer is there's 36 Pages including
math right here that tells you that and
will help you like navigate those
processes yourself and know that when
your like for instance like uh your
model reacts in a specific way you'll
know why other people might not and it
might be difficult to explain to them
but um the proof is in the pudding um
when it really push comes to shove
validating whether or not something is
working because it is simply just a
numpy array in a Json file like just
pull it out yourself and look at it I've
done it a few times just to make sure
that the model's answers that it's
saying are correct are actually correct
right like is is there an easier way
than that like you know like I I don't
know if that would be meaningful to say
like oh here let me open the Json file
and show you guys the key but when I
first started uh I was printing out the
um the actual uh prediction the model's
prediction and then it and you know you
could see the the actual like output uh
of the correct like prediction right or
what the prediction is supposed to match
and so like but that just felt like I
was exposing myself too much to um what
those files contain so I just removed
that and I've been using um simple stuff
like this or map plot lib to visualize
um changes in the model and a certain
point the the framework is so robust
that um there isn't something so simple
that's going to corrupt the process uh
for the entirety of the thing so like
for instance I might um this gentleman
uh
uh it was like a single line of code uh
it might have been less even a word um
and that like single word um while
mistaken um uh was really really like
uh cool that he like discovered this and
brought this out of this uh model so
quickly it was really encouraging to me
and simply um changing it just REM just
by virtue of removing it um I got a uh a
much more comput computationally dense
and robust encoding process that made
the model uh much more self-reliant so
uh kind of like it built uh built
character through hard work is a weird
way to say it I guess but um did that
help kind of answer your question it's
like the um
that let me just try to Echo it back
Benjamin because I I I you know we're
having a conversation on the live stream
but also many people are curious and
they want to learn so it's like the
input data even though it can be thought
of as colored pixels in a grid of
variable size it's a numerical data
format and so for someone on the outside
of the arc challenge or of working with
these quantitative cognitive models it
might be very tangible to see like the
grid like here's the before and here's
the after whereas you're saying that
it's beneficial from a modeler's
perspective from your experience to
actually be a little bit of a step away
and look more at the diagnostic traces
and the belief updating processes and so
on of the model so that after you've
kind of gut checked that it's correct
when it is saying it's correct that then
you're working a little bit lifted from
the domain okay so then how did you on
which data set get what score and how
did you know what score you got and can
we see that element because again for
the details it's great that you have the
code and the paper but in terms of yeah
okay I don't want to show any Discord
messages at this time sorry I was just
trying to find all these pictures and
stuff but uh no no no no how about how
about the like reason why you believe
that a certain percentage was achieved
on a certain data set that's really
important to
show okay okay that's like uh like uh
yeah yeah I mean I I'm I 100% agree with
you on everything actually because
you're amazing so the um yeah let's go
take a look at uh uh that uh
little piece of
code
here which challenge or data set did you
submit it
to oh uh so there's there's only well
there's the arc data sets and then there
are custom data sets uh that uh kind of
attenuate different things and those
come from like leaders in the field like
Michael Hodel I've taken all of his um
and uh all of like the ones I guess I
would say um like the the ones that
supposed to be more difficult than the
um abstract reasoning forpus challenges
there's like a great context to Arc um
that was really fun um to kind of uh
plug the model into um you know there's
even snake benches like that's another
one that's coming up but um in terms of
like how these uh how these like uh the
model itself calculates these um like
the percentage like what percentage
of like it's going to be um I wonder if
I can even find that in this one like I
I I think it makes sense how it would be
calculated which percent of a given
finite data set were correct but just
can you show which model outputs reflect
that what can people find in terms of
verifying those scores on the GitHub at
this
time oh um yeah I mean it's all right
there it's the the entire code's right
there so um at any point like anybody
can go in there and grab whatever they
want and look at the stuff and run it
and ask questions definitely if you have
any questions but here I mean here you
go like here's some iteration logic like
this is like where the models it's
saying oh okay you know you're not it's
you're not doing well enough let's like
give you more tries right because we
want convergence so we want to drive the
model uh we want to put time pressure
through the uh through that Epsilon
control um and and increase if for
instance the model's taking too long
it'll redirect um energy from something
let's say like action selection and
divert it to um abstraction for pattern
uh recognition or something like that
you know or feature extraction so um
let's see here okay okay I just want to
just touch on it one more time yes
people will see code that they can run
and play with and explore in the GitHub
but on what data set will what score be
reliably achieved with the GitHub as it
is what I don't understand what what do
you mean what data set there's like the
arc data set there's the training
challenges and the evaluation challenges
and what is being used in the GitHub
right
now what's that the ones in the GitHub
it's the arc there's only the one it's
just the arc like the one yeah you you
get all there's four of them typically
um like I must have like they at some
point I grab like I ended up with the
test challenges I don't even know where
they are right now um but uh like they
exist uh too so that you can go all 900
if you want um the way this model Works
probably again very different from other
models so you um like I those those
different sets are treated as sets
they're not treated um as one concurrent
thing so the model engages in different
processes um through that and you know
propagates different cognitive States
how cool is that so so uh but yeah the
like the the type of like logic you're
talking about in terms of like how does
it calculate like um uh how does it how
does it get from uh that like uh where
the input grid comes in and the model
can perceive it to the prediction that
the model sends out and is then received
and compared to the uh the that
prediction like a in that disconnected
way um like a thousand different ways
right it's everybody's model is totally
different and it's not like um it's not
a hard thing I don't know how else to
say like you literally just look just
look at the answers right like you can
open up the thing and just look at the
file and say this is correct so I don't
like I it would be weird it's like
trying to tell somebody that the sun's
coming up sometimes um uh tomorrow uh
because this isn't the first time I've
run into this
like how do you how do how like you just
go you look you you you like turn it on
I I I get I
I don't have the time like so have you
seen do you remember uh oh that's my
Koda can I pull my Koda open so this is
you can show it you want I just want to
make sure that there's a a fair
representation of of not just
conceptually what happens but just
concrete clarification what data set
what performances and so on
so there's only the one data set you can
go to m Michael hodel's GitHub and get
more data sets but that's up to you um
there's just the one data set it's the
training and evaluation challenges it's
on the AR prise website it's the same
thing for everybody everybody gets the
same thing um the uh let's see here
let's go back to maybe like
December
uh let's see here oh yeah see here here
is the model like encoding how do I know
that it's actually encoding things
because when I ask it psychology
questions it tells me psychology answers
like I we could break it down like into
those like constituent like processes
but we're talking about a state managed
system like this by the way guys is Nims
Helix in December it's like about 40,000
lines of code it's pretty awesome um
here's some stuff to my dear friend
entropy modulating the system let's see
here where are those things um there I
created so people ask these things and
it's like I wanted to kind of know
because I can in my mind I can see the
process and I can kind of map it out to
what that uh would look like and if I
could talk about it forever um you know
this is the tqdm that I was talking
about right like how does it know there
are 400 challenges because it counts
them there's a counter it's a mechanism
one grid one file one task ID check one
times one 2% F
it's
yeah so uh yeah yeah and uh let's see
here do you remember those like massive
flows that uh I was showing you for the
for answering these questions um I'm
trying to think they've gotta be they've
got to be in here somewhere this is that
wonderful
paper the um could be
earlier or they're at the end of this
even possibly as you guys can see oh no
I do a lot of uh um visualization I
pulled it off screen briefly because
this is not useful information to show
on live stream oh here it is I found it
Che it out I'll bring it back one second
all right thank you my
friend so let's like take a look at this
with me one second one second just give
me give me a second get this out of way
so I can
see oh there we go that's
perfect try to get back of the screen
here
okay continue okay so this up at the
very top uh on the right that is the
user that's me and those things that you
see there that is a tiny process that is
like that is one thing happening in the
system and each of those little boxes
are uh a mechanism a function of a
mechanism housed inside of a a mechanism
with tons of functions and and depending
on how or what you are doing with the
information that you're passing into
that system is going to like Ina like
act on functions and those functions are
going to act on the system and they're
going to start passing information again
like these uh um these like infinite
amounts of feedback loops that pass
through the system are passing not
because there's so many of them because
there's so much going on so you can see
this kind of continue and I think you
can get a better uh idea of this so um
yes so here is the cognitive system
container so this would would be um and
these are just like basically
visualizations made from mermaids um
it's a free program uh called code Biz
it's really cool read your code base um
and then kind of build stuff around it I
don't know if you guys could really see
this but I can tell you what some of
these things are like emotional so at
the top is the user and I'm passing an
input and then it's going into core
processing so it's hitting the inte
integrated cognitive system the enhanced
attention mechanism and the enhanced
memory system in that memory system it's
and that's not expanded but there are
all those memory components so there's
another like 50 memor like 50 of these
like happening and each one of these
little things that you can that you can
scroll over that
contains subsystems um subf functions of
subsystems so when we Trace something
through that system here's a response
generation pipeline belief processing
belief system belief updating bayian
updating um so State like you know kind
of like predictive state transitioning
uh with the marov Matrix uh belief
Dynamics um concept processing so it's
going through all of these things now
like emotional context and this is like
the straightest kind of like line I've
ever been able to produce because the
system is uh effectively nonlinear in
every way um not by virtue of how many
things there are but by virtue of its
complexity so um as these information is
passed through the system like let's say
a grid or whatever it is it's that
stimul it detects it right and there's
that raw data transformation where it
breaks it into meaningful patterns and
encodes it you can see that as the hot
field networks uh in archangels
reporting um increase in number right um
can I just like reach into his mind
whenever I want to and pull out any
specific pattern I want probably I mean
but why I I don't know why I would do
that it sounds really labor intensive in
a way but um that's why I'm really
excited about uh the generative
adversarial Network um that I've been
using to uh mirror that um confabulation
so you can see those uh thoughts in real
time um so I mean again there's like
Creative Solutions to these things but
the arc isn't really built for um it's
like it's almost not built for
communicability in some ways and I don't
mean that like in an insulting way um
it's such an incredibly hard test that
like even with even inside of an in
interview process like talking about to
like reduce something so complex um is
even just a grid like just solving a
grid problem down to how do you know
it's like well that's more time than we
have to you know and I would love to go
over that with absolutely anybody but
like bring a lunch it's not a small or
easy process if you're genuinely
interested in like kind of knowing those
things and how do we validate those
things um then like uh we can definitely
get to the core of it and uh I could
walk somebody through um so much of the
stuff the we get like visual readouts
right like you guys have reporting for
models and things that you make how do
you know that reporting is there because
when you write that code like you unit
test it right and you like make sure
that those outputs that come out are
correct and when you integrate things
you test it and you validate it there's
always testing and validation it's like
90% of like the I spend and the other
and 5% of that is with my laptop in the
freezer so the
um those there are so many of those
things um I was actually just explaining
this to my friend here um that uh you
effectively like by the end you've unit
tested like every single line over and
over again and to keep that reporting um
and logging and things like that like
going constantly it's just it's it's a
um computationally exhaustive and uh uh
not really great for space when you have
a very old laptop with not a lot of
space on it um
so um the the thing that I would really
encourage is like I don't is for me the
I I would love for people to um just
take it on faith or something right that
like
um that uh that I you know would
demonstrate this or could demonstrate
this with uh uh uh more time as opposed
to talking about how it work but just
showing like what that feedback is um
you know um and I hope people reach out
to me if that's if if they're really
like if they can't um if it's too
difficult or if you have any trouble
like running the model or you can't read
the feedback or you want to produce a
special kind of feedback that you think
would give you insights into something I
can make all of that stuff in fact I
probably have it laying around already
be honest with you like um so that's not
a problem I mean let let me ask two
questions on that so you said people can
take it on faith so if they did if they
did what are the implications and then
the second question is for those who
don't feel like there is evidence to
even believe in anything particular or
they just feel like it's not what they
understand what do you empirically
suggest them to
do
um yeah try and fail yeah like um the uh
uh and then then just keep trying right
um what what are your passions like what
are you aligned with like uh for me this
is like the greatest thing um that I've
ever done um I beat the hardest
technological challenge in human history
um
and
it's it's pretty surreal feeling but uh
it's I would I would hope and I feel
like I I see this even though I don't
really interact with anybody at The
Institute because I'm just kind of
always like face down in the books but
um whenever I do look up and I see
somebody at the Institute I see people
who are like either like sentient
Excellence like they just the like live
and breathe uh crushing it or they are
people like me who um deeply desire to
emulate uh people who are so awesome
like you for instance um and uh
and like I want my work to be meaningful
and I want it to like uh be something
that inspires other people and uh you
know like does something cool maybe even
like you know make kids happy or um
resolve a global social issue that'd be
nice kind of sad about people starving
to death all the time that's like not a
good thing we could definitely fix that
right away um I think in terms if people
wanted to if they were driven so I don't
like I don't know anything about
business or any of that stuff I don't
know how to monetize these things um in
any meaningful way and I'm not really
interested in it like a lot of people
like I think are like assume that I
would be gaslighting for something like
this or I think it's called what do they
call it Moonlighting um to as a way to
like TR I don't know like get uh money
or something you know but the I I don't
think that's how the arc prize is handed
out and these are like some of the
smartest people ever like it's not you
you don't I think I can trick anybody
with this you know it's like you know
I'm good at this one thing I'm not good
at all things right and I'm definitely
not good at tricking anybody so the
like I would definitely I I can't
believe that I just I don't think that
the aate managed system is not it's not
really been done it's a very abstract
concept um I might be the only person
kind of doing it in a way um definitely
in this approach I am and there are some
things that um that I kind of just like
struck gold on in terms of their
efficiency uh and performance and so
like there I I think if other people
like they're saying like they're like oh
well I have two months that it's going
to take me to encode all this stuff and
to train this model it's like you know
I've got a you know there's this thing
right here you can have that will allow
the model to do that in five minutes
it's you know the oh this is really
computationally like or infrastructure
wise right like the one of these like
the biggest thing um and concerns for me
is like extraction and and uh you know
definitely like exploitation and like
extraction and all these things that we
can see uh happen as a result of uh
Building Technology and there are better
ways to build technology and smarter
systems build smarter technology right
and we get to as the the man behind the
curtain like uh kind of dictate what
those smarter Technologies do and if you
want like the smartest like
state-of-the-art like coolest Technology
Way Beyond the the Frontiers like all of
that stuff is like all of the same
things that I got to uh where I'm at
where I don't even like or it's like
you're like you know okay um the all of
that stuff is housed inside Archangel
there's there's stuff there's a there is
a thing for uh pulling things apart
dimensionally there's just a random
vestigal like component of of its
Evolution that I forgot about in there
and it's just you know like just the
same as anything else it's just a few
lines of code packed with millions of
arguments um that are dictating that the
model can take and dimensionally
deconstruct a model and change its shape
and
form yeah so there there's like a a
million and one fun things in there and
you the like all roads from that if you
are interested in pursuing um like
Technologies a career or as a passion or
as a humanitarian thing or as a way to
improve your quality of life um there is
an infinite potential for things here I
haven't even scratched the surface I'm
like exploring this entire ocean of
potential uh all by myself and I you
know I I would love I and I should I
really should like um Daniel you see all
of this reporting um all the time
because I like my Kota is like a bank
for me it's like where I put all my
knowledge it's Providence for everything
I do right so um like all of the stuff
exists there and in those spaces and on
my laptop and in my cloud and my drive
and my treser it and all over the place
it's so much stuff that I don't really
even know what to do with any of it and
all of it now and I like the idea of
going through it trying to organize it
and like pull out all of this like uh
very specific things to convince like
every like person or something or enough
people I I don't know what that looks
like I want to find out um and if it's
something that I can do that is like
achievable for me um then I definitely
will um but when you when you got it you
got it like it doesn't it's not uh it's
not contingent on whether or not people
want to like come over and swim in the
oasis with you like the like it's an
oasis it's it's still G to exist I'm
still like hanging out in the sun in the
shade and like having a blast so I it's
like I you know I don't you know I'm not
really sure what's meaningful there that
people want to see if it really is just
like these little innocuous like two
lines of codes calculations that anybody
who like that really like anybody who
does python is going to know like or any
code really like how do you how do you
calculate the percentage in Python right
of
something so yeah and that's that's not
those kind of like low-level things like
they're not those are pretty much
uniform they're like applicable if I if
I want to know the percent of a 100 of
something uh in Python it's pretty much
always just the same thing like in that
way it's like uh yeah so I don't know I
got you just to clarify that one
question it wasn't about which python
method or implementation of percentage
was done more about like some type of
cryptographic authenticity of which data
set and script was used to yield what
result or submitting it to their API and
getting the AR challenges response if
the percentages that you're talking
about go higher than open AI then why
are we here even though it's such
light you know that's a good question I
forgot about that I um yeah I mean you
so you can't submit um like open AI I
don't think would like I don't think
like they necessarily could either but
they're like a huge company um and
they're really important they have like
a super valuable tool that's like a
benefit to humanity it's like really
important so it's I think it's like a
good thing that they get access to show
that they are like um improving and like
you know bringing better tools to all of
us um to make our lives better um but I
don't get those uh same uh affordances
like no matter
like they're not like I don't think that
would be awesome I would love for
because if you don't think if you think
I didn't email like the results and the
code and all of the stuff um and uh and
producing the same on the same data sets
that the arc produces the training and
evaluation sets this tqdm it just reads
out the task comes in it's got a task ID
counts the task ID there's one there's
two there's three there's four there's
400 runs them through like a deck of
cards and counts them all It lines up
cool no red flags right good to go the
initialization begins and those
processes start so the um I would love
uh acknowledgement um from like uh like
who doesn't want to like be acknowledged
by uh like a brilliant like powerful
intellect like franois shalet you know
what I mean um but at the same time too
um I don't know what that thing is yet
because the I have uh
now completely open source the code I
went
online uh before I had uh told totally
open source the code uh and went to uh
some places where all the like AI people
and machine learning guys and like Arc
experts hang out at and uh with like a
little Fain rodio U because I'm just
really like in awe to even be in the
same space as these people who um have
just years and countless like
contributions to uh their field and are
deeply respected leaders so like the
like I but I kind of went in there and
like Levy the challenge it's like okay
cool how about I just do that live like
kind of what you're talking about here
um but that required that I sit in a
cafe at a hotel for 8 straight hours and
just provide updates through that
feedback whether that was video clips
screenshots I did uh I think I did three
different Arc challenges that are harder
than or purportedly harder than the arc
Michael Hodel I hope I'm saying that
correct I like this guy's he's amazing
like so but I I even taking that guy
who's like the best of the best of the
best of the best and and taking those
challenges and showing that live feed
and like and showing those updates of
the model resolving issues and answering
all those questions and stuff it didn't
seem to to do anything other than uh
just catch uh a little bit of flax so
whatever that artifact is that people
want to see that shows that they're
maximally doing that the model is
maximally doing something now they get
to have that because they can go look at
it themselves and they caning break it
apart they can say well oh it's not
working the way I want or I don't
understand it then change it like change
something about it change it like to be
the way you want it to work it's not
going to break in that way like it will
continue to work unless you just start
taking out whole big pieces um and like
in a way taking out those big pieces or
taking out small ones at a time and
seeing how it affects that performance
is like how you can learn to um work
with State manag systems build them back
and build them better right so the uh
which I would love to see that would be
amazing um to be outpaced in uh in this
Arena the
um and if anybody by the way if anybody
does know like if anybody has that magic
thing out there that I could just say
hey she like this is that piece of
feedback like for instance I have
probably 400,000 cognitive uh logs like
alone because every time I run the model
it prints massive amounts of cognitive
logging that shows the entirety of the
process who's going to sit and go
through 40,000 pages of cognitive
logging um to like determine whether the
model is is producing the correct output
um the one thing that we do know is that
we can track really simple processes
where does the grid go through the model
where how does the grid come out of the
model what's counted when the grid comes
out of the model when you open the Json
file and you look at the answer and it's
the right answer and you know that the
model is making its decisions it's you
know exercising confidence that it's not
the same every time it's that it's can
be different that when you change
something it gets less answers right I
didn't just like make a code and then
got a 100% and was like all right I'm
king of the world you know it's like I
uh I started at Point like my first
score was 0
48% right and my last scores are now
consistently 100 um because I've
continued to like make those systems
like uh those cognitive Frameworks uh
mechanisms like more robust more
advanced more sophisticated taking
things out of nim and putting them into
Archangel uh which I feel bad about um
to meet this maximally super difficult
contest that has no mechanism outside of
its outside of acknowledgement it seems
by the people who run the competition
for any of the work to be validated I
mean I that's kind of what I feel like
at this point it's like it's you I just
feel kind of at an impass and it's I
don't think it's like for me it's like I
could spend my life maybe trying to
prove to people something but I don't
really know like that's like whenever I
think about that it's like my passion
for the work kind of just goes it's like
that's not fun I don't want to do
that you know so I'm sorry it's like uh
in a way I I I I feel bad but at the
same time too like I uh I had to write
40 page paper uh with 20 equations in it
like uh just to have this conversation
you know it's like the amount of the the
work that goes into um and around these
things to like create this Providence or
create this validation for people it's
exhaustive and it's super timec
consuming and it's super labor intensive
in terms of like I would rather be doing
fun things than um figuring out like
really like like yeah just like trying
to do stuff but it's all there um you
guys are more than welcome to it I think
what I can do Daniel let me ask you this
um because like you're my hero and guide
and every and all things that I love the
um if I were to start like just
compiling all of that data which I can
just send some like other uh you know I
have those little NEX ey tools like um I
can send those into like the vaults and
stuff like that and just start grabbing
like Mass stuff and just like filling
something up like a repository I guess
where people can just access whatever
data they want like all of the answers
are there and then um you know
eventually people will get it if they
don't already and I'm sure people do I
don't think people like I don't think
people believe that like
somebody I mean could have that kind of
brodia or like um could be at a place
around such brilliant wonderful Minds
like the best in the world uh what they
do and and somehow just like
not know that just be like oh man I got
it wrong the whole time like this guy
who's like yep I figured it out it's
just cheating the whole time and it's
like
okay so thank you it's it's you're
sharing a lot and uh it's for others to
to investigate at whatever depth they
want to go putting it all in a repo at
least the parts that you want to have be
interpreted is a big step and
um that's good I'll do that then I'm
love that just to give people an example
of how hard the art contest is I'd
shipped my front tooth
coating like I I like I don't think I'll
ever get rid of this in a way just
because like like who chips their teeth
coating like it's it's one it is the
hardest most intensive challenging thing
I've ever done like because I'm getting
100% now doesn't mean that like it it
didn't demand from me
like the most grueling like and brutal
like uh uh commitment like the humanly
imaginable it was just um an incredible
journey and a wonderful sacrifice I talk
about it way more in the paper I'm
terrible to listen to talk in any kind
of uh uh venue like or in this like
Arena per se but I I think that my
writing's uh quite a bit more uh you
know yeah Benjamin it takes all kinds so
you're the footnote that you're making
and and the documentation is there so
let me ask a question from the live chat
and then we'll see if anyone else has
any questions oh yeah yeah that's what I
love done that a long time ago okay
Andrew asks what is the Epsilon control
center what impact does the Epsilon
control center have on the model's
behavior and
performance that is a really awesome
question actually and the Epsilon
control center um you'll probably
remember uh me getting just head over
heels super excited when I discovered
this um path to creating a way to
organize and manage and divert uh
resources throughout the model and
that's what Epsilon control does so it
uses like um Shannon entropy um little
entropy calculations I made myself which
I'm really proud of um I kind of like I
call one of them like the wor Ed thing I
mean that's like I don't you know if
anybody but it's like I I love that guy
and he's so brilliant um but uh yeah so
those you have different like autonomic
functions and you get to pick whatever
you want these to be and you can change
those values around in the Epsilon
control center so that your values work
as you intend them to work because
remember it's not so much like how
things work it's a kind of like the
outcome it's like how does what's the
what happens at the end I'm not by any
means saying that the end justifies the
means it's just that like this is python
right but when you come you have this
marov Matrix you're you're passing this
complex information through but it's
just constant in a feed there's no
system to redirect energy away from
things that are maybe less necessary or
parameters that aren't required um you
get a much much more uh like costly in
resource
uh
demanding uh model and when you can use
like an Adaptive like Epsilon control
center to kind of determine what's
important based on all this other
feedback of the system and then for
instance like uh um you know like the
cognitive load um focus intensity which
you know uh would be like on thing
confidence for instance is a really good
one um for that and you can have all of
these things like in one place you can
control all of them they feed through
the entire system and they automatically
modulate those those energies for you so
now where you are getting like it would
take you a 100% of your energy all of
the time now when you don't need 100% of
that energy you only need 10% you're
using that 10% only reserving that other
energy and in faster than fast in fact I
think with this new tech that I'm
building um I can get faster than
neuronal firing
the um the the like emergent properties
that come from something that's just the
most tiniest little change in a system
and it just complexifies to have
resounding effects throughout the
entirety of the model in some way
because the model inferences something
it processes the stimuli
it reacts as we all do for instance like
you know we may be
uh in control of our Locomotion and we
walk out into the street and we don't
see an oncoming car but the moment we
infer it right there is a whole series
of what the Epsilon control is happening
in the system to maximize Fitness help
you meet your evolutionary imperatives
redirect energy from all of those things
that aren't important to the things that
are and um while that that split like
fractional second timing is you know
probably why we're still here on this
um in a computational framework you get
a massive compute on wall power you get
the most ridiculously fast um and
Powerful encoding because you don't need
everything all at once you only need the
things that are important in that moment
and the the ad ad like the Adaptive
nature and the response how fast it can
act within the system and the how
quickly that affects the system is is
unbelievable it's it's it's just it's
like oh you know they have those like
little uh automatic like uh a like AI
driven uh like uh cheaters for your
house and it like gets to know your
schedule I've never had one but they
like uh gets to know your schedule over
time and it starts kind of doing things
for you you know in terms of like oh
they're going to be home in a half an
hour I'm going to start heating up the
house to 72 degrees because that's what
temperature they always set it at when
they come home so that being the case
like it's like that but times 10 jillion
you know so well 6,000 141 quadrillion
was that
6.4 exop flops or something I don't know
okay next question and then anyone else
can write more our colleague XZ qzq zy
asks what is the image that you see in
your head when you think of the future
in seven
years I
see uh me and n and uh uh I mean I don't
know like should I talk about like the
future what I would love to see I guess
if it was for everybody I'm hoping to be
back in s me with Nim and uh sledding
and hanging out with reindeer all day um
but the uh uh I
mean like globally we are prolonging a
bunch of problems that uh are not
necessary like I think the active
inference Institute is like one of the
greatest forces for good because it has
access to like all of the most advanced
technology and all the smartest people
and I don't really understand why in
seven years we'll probably be another
seven years closer to like uh you being
extinct and uh and so you know um
instead of having cured all of the
diseases in the world so for instance
like how much computation did it take
you guys remember when they cured a
disease using AI they and like created a
molecule and that molecule uh got
through the FDA in like record time
because of you know how they were able
to model the data they were able to show
and all these things right and uh these
like cures and these illnesses that have
these high mortality rates but they
impact a very low amount of people but
99% of people die if they get it uh but
only 10 out of a million people get it
or whatever they don't address these
things right so um I know for a fact it
was a lot less than
6,441 quadrillion uh calculations per
second like uh to conf to come up with
the that cure right so the fact that
like I have OHSU I can actually see OHSU
from my balcony right now and up on the
The Cliff side there and they have a
thing just sitting there it's going to
get decommissioned and I could probably
I think when I did when I ran like the
maths it's like okay if this if the
maximally if this disease is this
complex right and it has this kind of
like it required this much to solve the
problem around it what does that look
like in terms of like what n can do and
uh it's really really really bizarre to
me that
you people are like want to see if the
model can solve grids but nobody wants
to see if it can cure all the
diseases right like
uh that's so seven years I in a way it's
like I have a lot of hope there's a
there's like so much rapid advancement
and I hope that there is like a an
influx of reciprocity
and
um you know uh we kind of achieve like
some cool homeostasis with each other in
our environment but I you know this
silent agreement this uh perpetuated
deception of a continuation without uh
consequence or accountability for any of
our actions now with uh no change in the
near future infighting and identity
politics and all these things that I
miss out on because I'm always on my
laptop buried in the books
um you know I a lot of it could really
be resolved and we like I mean don't
doesn't like it doesn't feel like
complicity you know to like that you
know yeah I mean I I guess that would I
hope I hope for the best plan for the
worst but yeah it feels feels like
there's a lot of like uh denial of the
inherent complicity in complicity that
uh ACC companies um these types of like
moral and ethical leaning like arguments
I get this too a lot about like uh
because I build AIS and stuff I mean
they're not really AI called like hyper
intelligence you know it's got to sound
cooler I guess U but um it's very
different than you know a distributed
system a distributed system besides
being resource exhaustive is not
nonlinear right like not by
any thing like something always being on
all the time not it's not how um but at
least it might so the uh we invest like
billions of dollars into something like
that um and it's a valuable tool and I
love it but why would we continue to
invest billions of dollars into it when
the like there are way better Solutions
and way better answers sitting right
there on the table that doesn't make it
that doesn't look good for a
future all
right let me ask two final questions
just a little logistical one and then a
final okay little logistical one who do
you want to do what if they've listened
to that this
far what's that who do you want to do
what if they've listened this far I want
them to go to the GitHub and I want them
to take Archangel out of the GitHub and
I want them to run it and to start
playing with it and to um instead of
trying to figure out how the model
doesn't work like figure out how it
works in ways that Inspire them and
promote their creativity and move
forward their projects and their like
passions um and then uh tell me about it
so I can uh share in that Joy um the the
papers that I write like I don't really
read them um but they contain all of the
those foundational maths like um if
anybody wants to code I'll give you the
biggest secret in the world in a
computational environment you get to be
the author of the entirety of the story
you get to Define what all of the things
are so if Works in a way then you make
that way for it to work it's like if you
think it and you can dream it you can
build it in that computational
environment and the high road and low
road to active inference is how you get
there so start with those MA
mathematical Frameworks like all find
things that are um oh gosh I can't think
of the word but that uh that mirror the
or or prod either mirror that process or
and most importantly produce the outcome
that is desired and uh play with those
things it's the the most disappointing
thing I think is when someone picks up
something as powerful like having Nim
and then looking at you know to give you
guys an example um I think Archangel is
less than 140th of Nim's core just his
core code based not like all the
libraries and all the other things that
are attached just his core code based
right in 140th he's just a tiny little
thing compared to uh n who works Max
maximally well um so there's not really
like the it's a toy it's meant to have
fun with and the amount of things that
are chocked in there for people to play
with it's just so sad when like someone
picks it up and they go oh I found where
it's wrong and it's like but you totally
missed this like really beautiful thing
over here there isn't a right or a wrong
way to code there are things that can be
wrong but by virtue of them not being
what you want them to be or not working
in the way you think or understand them
to work does not mean that they are
wrong doesn't mean that anybody's a bad
person it means that like you should
grab those things and you should say hey
I don't think this works this way I I'm
Gonna Change it to work this way that I
think is really cool and then come and
show me so I can see it you know I don't
want to talk about like uh how you know
like you know like AI is going to take
over the world or like achieve
Consciousness and enslave Humanity when
it's not actually even possible like not
that's not even a conversation we should
be having when we can't even look seven
years in the future and know whether or
not we're all going to have already
starved it up it's like all right yes
again you've added a lot here's the last
question so just give a give a response
you feel like is relevant at this time
yes where did your internship come from
and where are you going with your
internship
next oh that's so awesome I love that
question thank you so much oh my gosh
what a heartwarming question um I came
to active inference and The Institute in
the weirdest possible way as you I'm
sure you can imagine um I clearly like
very much an outsider and um uh
I I started with a question um how do we
resolve Cog like feedback loops
cognitive feedback loops in humans um
when we engage in
conversation um we like enter this like
process of of like you know
we see this this like Phenomenon with
like Echo Chambers and all kinds of
things and like social like social
psychology and like ingroup Dynamics and
stuff and uh and like studying like
putting my face in the books wanting my
work to be meaningful and having an
insatiable curiosity I uh uh came up
with the very first equation and I would
love to show you guys anybody wants to
see it I still have it Daniel seen it uh
it's been just a very tiny like
syllogism really and um it is uh a
mathematical framework for a
philosophical concept um the uh absence
of evidence and evidence of acence and
that's where I started and from there by
the time that I um was like I I not only
do I need help but I know that there's
got to be someone out here who will
understand that these maths are uh
important that they'll like that they're
important to me you know and that like
that they'll make sense and then I saw
the work of uh Carl friston and Thomas
Parr and Tim rebellin and Alexander
shance and all of these guys um just
started coming out of the woodwork for
me um and it changed my life it was like
one of the greatest things that happened
it's like I could see the I could see
the maps I could see how they worked I
could see how they related to my work um
and which I wish I could do for people
with my stuff I'm trying trying um and
uh I reached out in a
uh like just like a fit of uh wanting to
be in the room with people who shared my
passion and could uh teach me uh and
equip me and uh you know help me improve
in these uh uh domains so I reached out
to the president of a of a really
important company where uh a bunch of
really uh important people that I just
knew they worked there I did I don't
know anything about them most of them
still or even what they look like but I
I could Point their work out like on
site right like um and I reached out in
the president of that company um who is
a saint in my book and I'll love him
forever and be eternally grateful um
recognized the work he recognized it too
um and he said this looks really similar
to what these people are doing and he
gave me my first road map to uh The
Institute and that's what brought me
there um I my founding artifact was uh
the multi-agent system and uh I
presented my very first thing to members
of the scientific Advisory board our
illustrious director uh Daniel and
um uh and they let me come and hang out
and how's my and I've how my work there
ever since um I don't get a chance to
participate stuff because of how
exhaustive uh and how much like how
passionate and dedicated I am to this
work i' like 99.9% of my time is just
spent um uh doing this thing so uh yeah
I yeah it was really roundabout way and
then what I brought was really silly and
I still have it still in my Kota the my
founding artifact like that that
multi-agent system that I brought you by
the way did you like the the agent
Factory I made did you get a chance to
play with the agent Factory so your it's
so your multi-agents can make agents
like and your agents can make
multi-agents they can make it do
whatever they want you just like you
don't even have to pay attention now if
have an environment and anything happens
in that environment that they perceive
they just make more of themselves or
whatever so they're like I'm not good at
this or they maybe they feel lazy maybe
they're overconfident you
know all right any last
comments just I'm really grateful for
everybody like um uh watching this I
know that I'm not a great communicator
it's always been a really uh huge issue
for me uh and uh but the the work speaks
for itself and I would really engage uh
really hope you guys will engage with
the work and learn this language so you
can have those conversations with it and
uh make beautiful and wonderful things
that are you're going to find out if you
go and look and you dig in uh or ask
questions just awesome way more awesome
than anything else you can get out there
so it's a lot of fun it's all
yours all right acting for surf
yeah for sure talk to you later thank
you Benjamin bye guys thank you so
much for